I hope you all are doing very well.
आशा करता हूं आप सब बहुत अच्छे होंगे।
My name is Siddhant Agnihotri.
मेरा नाम है सिद्धांत अग्निहोत्री। स्टडी
Welcome to Study Gloss.
ग्लोस पे आपका बहुत-बहुत स्वागत है।
Friends, this will be my analysis and I will
दोस्तों ये मेरा एनालिसिस रहेगा और मैं
tell you what I think.  But
क्या सोचता हूं मैं आपको बताऊंगा। लेकिन
before that I want to tell you that
उससे पहले मैं आपको बताना चाहता हूं कि
our amazing YouTube SEO Plus Thumbnail
हमारा जो शानदार YouTube एसइओ प्लस थंबनेल
course is live.
का कोर्स है वो लाइव है। रिकॉर्डेड
You will get recorded lectures.  The
लेक्चर्स आपको मिलेंगे। डिस्क्रिप्शन
link is given in the description comment box.  And if you
कमेंट बॉक्स में लिंक दिया है। और अगर आप
want, you can avail this course.  The
चाहें तो इस कोर्स को अवेल करिए। मात्र
course costs just ₹400.  You will use the YouTube coupon code.
₹400 का कोर्स है। YouTube कूपन कोड आप
You will benefit a lot.
यूज़ करेंगे। आपको बहुत ज्यादा फायदा होगा।
Ok?  So this offer is till tomorrow because then we will
ओके? तो कल तक ये ऑफर है क्योंकि फिर हम
close this offer.  Meaning the sale will
इस ऑफर को बंद कर देंगे। मतलब सेल जो है
come after three-four months.  So, many such
तीन-चार महीने बाद आएगी। तो ये काफी
articles have been published.
आर्टिकल छपे हैं। ऑपरेशन का के बारे में
I told you about the operation.  Israel was the one that was going to
मैंने आपको बताया था। इजराइल जो है वो
attack.  In what way
हमला करने वाला था। किस तरीके से
I took a complete lecture on Pakistan from there.
पाकिस्तान के ऊपर उसमें मैंने पूरा लेक्चर
But let me tell you that
लिया था। लेकिन मैं बता दूं कि इंदिरा
this offer was made during the time of Indira Gandhi and earlier during the time of Morarji Desai.  It
गांधी ने और पहले मोरारजी देसाई के समय ये
is Indira Gandhi.  He had
ऑफर था। इंदिरा गांधी हैं। उन्होंने मना
refused.  Right?  And after that Rajiv
कर दिया था। राइट? और उसके बाद फिर राजीव
Gandhi again refused.  So basically all three of them
गांधी ने मना कर दिया था। तो तीनों ने ही
had refused.  But Israel and
मना कर दिया था बेसिकली। बट इजराइल और
India together were going to destroy Pakistan.  They were going to
भारत मिलकर पाकिस्तान को तबाह करने वाले
destroy their nuclear program.
थे। उनके न्यूक्लियर प्रोग्राम को तबाह
Now friends, let's talk about something.  Is it
करने वाले थे। अब दोस्तों हम कुछ बात करते
okay?  I will tell you three-four points.
हैं। ठीक है ना? तीन-चार पॉइंट्स मैं आपको
According to me, it was a big blunder on India's part
मेरे हिसाब से इंडिया का ये बहुत बड़ा
that they did not say yes.  He should have
ब्लंडर था कि उन्होंने यस नहीं बोला। उनको
said yes.  Why?  Look at the situation in Iran today.
यस बोलना चाहिए था। क्यों? आज आप ईरान के
Iran does not have a nuclear bomb, rather
ईरान के पास न्यूक्लियर बम नहीं है बल्कि
Iran calls itself a Muslim leader.
ईरान मुस्लिम लीडर कहता है अपने आप को
You are considering itself a Muslim leader.
मुस्लिम लीडर आप समझ रहे हो पूरी दुनिया
Iran calls itself a Muslim leader in the entire world
में ईरान जो है अपने आप को मुस्लिम लीडर
and Iran does not have nuclear power, so
कहता है और ईरान के पास न्यूक्लियर पावर
it is helpless. The day
नहीं है तो वो बेबस है जिस दिन यहां पे
nuclear power comes here, things will change.
न्यूक्लियर पावर आएगी चीजें बदल जाएंगी
If we talk about Pakistan, now
पाकिस्तान की अगर हम बात करते हैं अब आप
see Pakistan in this context, look at this country, this country has been for
देखिए इस देश को देखिए ये देश जो है वो
sale since the beginning and it has
शुरू से ही बिकाऊ रहा है और इसने अमेरिका
supported America by saying that keep giving us alms
का ही सपोर्ट किया है कि हमको भीख देते
and we will keep doing your work.  Is it okay
रहो और हम आपका काम करते रहेंगे। ठीक है
?  Now when the war with Pakistan took place in 1971,
ना? अब पाकिस्तान जब 1971 वॉर होती है तो
India fully destroyed Pakistan within 13 days.
भारत ने फुल फ्लेजेड 13 दिन के अंदर-अंदर
After that, we
पाकिस्तान को तोड़ दिया। उसके बाद हमने
took control of 1/3 of their army.
इनकी 1/3 सेना को अपने कब्जे में ले लिया।
Then they freed him and took him away.  Meaning, he came, Shimla
फिर ये छुड़ा के ले गए। मतलब ये आए शिमला
agreement was signed and he said that it is no big deal,
एग्रीमेंट हुआ और बोला कि चलो कोई बात
take it.  Indira Gandhi showed a big heart and
नहीं ले जाओ। इंदिरा गांधी ने बड़ा दिल
said, okay you can take it.
दिखाते हुए बोला कि ठीक है आप ले जाइए।
But friends, in 1974 we
लेकिन दोस्तों 1974 में हमने अपना
conducted our nuclear test and we got the
न्यूक्लियर टेस्ट किया और हमारे पास
nuclear power capability.
न्यूक्लियर पावर कैपेबिलिटी आ गई हमारे
Then Pakistan started building its own nuclear power.
पास। फिर पाकिस्तान अपना न्यूक्लियर पावर
Nuclear.  Abdul Qadeer Khan,
बनाने लगा। न्यूक्लियर। अब्दुल कादिर खान,
Abdul Salam, all these people,
अब्दुल सलाम ये जितने भी लोग हैं ना
they stole the nuclear blueprints.
इन्होंने न्यूक्लियर ब्लूप्रिंट्स जो है
Abdul Qadeer Khan
वो चुराए। अब्दुल कादिर खान ने न्यूक्लियर
stole nuclear blueprints from Europe and
ब्लूप्रिंट्स चुराए यूरोप से और उसको
started selling them.  We were already developing our own nuclear
बेचना शुरू कर दिया। अपना तो न्यूक्लियर
programme.  Israel
प्रोग्राम बना ही रहे थे। इजराइल को यही
feared this.  They sold it to Libya, they
डर लगा। इन्होंने लीबिया को बेचा, नॉर्थ
sold it to North Korea, they sold it to Iran, they
कोरिया को बेचा, इन्होंने ईरान को बेचा,
sold it to Iraq.  Sold them all.  Pakistan has
इराक को बेचा। इन सबको बेचा। पाकिस्तान ने
made this a business.  So Israel said
ये धंधा बना लिया। तो इजराइल ने ये बोला
that let's do one thing together and
कि एक काम करते हैं मिलकर हम पाकिस्तान के
destroy the nuclear reactors of Pakistan.
न्यूक्लियर रिएक्टर्स को तबाह कर देते
Now what benefit would India get from this?
हैं। अब इससे भारत को फायदा क्या होता?
Pakistan was very scared in 1971.  These
पाकिस्तान बहुत ज्यादा डर गया था 1971। ये
CIA documents of 1993 reveal
1993 के सीआईए के डॉक्यूमेंट्स बताते हैं
that Pakistan was so scared that we
कि पाकिस्तान इतना डरा हुआ था कि हम
can never defeat India in a conventional war.
कन्वेंशनल वॉर से कभी जीत नहीं सकते भारत
So we will have to make a nuclear bomb.
से। तो हमको न्यूक्लियर बम बनाना पड़ेगा।
Ok?  Now suppose India had
ठीक है? अब अगर मान लीजिए कि भारत उस समय
accepted Israel's proposal at that time.  So this would have
इजराइल की बात मान लेता। तो इससे
ended Pakistan's nuclear program
पाकिस्तान का न्यूक्लियर प्रोग्राम खत्म
and Pakistan could not have done anything
होता और पाकिस्तान कुछ भी नहीं कर सकता था
because it knew that we will
क्योंकि उसको पता है कि हम भारत से वॉर
not be able to win the war against India.  We will not be able to win the war against India.
नहीं जीत पाएंगे। हम भारत से युद्ध नहीं
So if this had been a joint operation,
जीत पाएंगे। तो अगर ये एक जॉइंट ऑपरेशन
imagine how much damage Pakistan would have suffered
होता तो सोचिए पाकिस्तान को कितना नुकसान
and it would not have been able to become a nuclear power till date.
होता और आज तक वो न्यूक्लियर पावर नहीं बन
That means Pakistan would have been
सकता। यानी कि पाकिस्तान ड्यू
nuclearised.  Pakistan cannot be declared in today's time.
न्यूक्लियराइज हो जाता। आज के समय में
Donald Trump is currently sitting and having lunch with Asif Munir.
डॉनल्ड ट्रंप इस समय आसिफ मुनीर के साथ
So you forget it.   Is it
लंच कर रहे हैं बैठ के। तो आप भूल जाइए।
okay?  But that was a great opportunity.
ठीक है ना? लेकिन वो बहुत अच्छा मौका था।
So now there is no terrorism
तो अब कोई भी टेररिज्म होता ही नहीं
because if there was terrorism, suppose there was any
क्योंकि आतंकवाद होता मान लीजिए कोई
terrorism, then we could have attacked Pakistan
टेररिज्म होता तो हम पाकिस्तान पर हमला
or taught Pakistan a lesson,
बोल सकते थे या पाकिस्तान को सबक सिखा
Pakistan would have remained within its limits,
सकते थे पाकिस्तान अपनी औकात में रहता
but as soon as it
लेकिन जैसे ही 1998 में उसने अपना
conducted its nuclear test in 1998, its tone changed,
न्यूक्लियर टेस्ट किया उसके सुर बदल गए
till then it was silent, we snatched Siachen,
उससे पहले तक वो चुप था हमने सियाचिन छीना
we did everything, it was not saying much and
हमने सब कुछ वो ज्यादा बोल नहीं रहा था और
America also withdrew its support from Pakistan,
अमेरिका भी पाकिस्तान से हाथ खींच लिया था
but as soon as it became a nuclear power,
लेकिन जैसे जैसे ही न्यूक्लियर पावर बना
its tone changed and it
वो उसके बाद उसके सुर बदल गए और उसने
started carrying out horrific terrorist attacks and
भयानक तरीके से आतंकी हमला शुरू किया और
then it started giving nuclear threats to India again and again
फिर वो न्यूक्लियर धमकी बार-बार भारत को
and somewhere or the other the entire world also
देने लगा और कहीं ना कहीं पूरी दुनिया भी
listened to it, that is why America also
उसकी बात सुनती अमेरिका भी इसीलिए
helped Pakistan because nuclear
पाकिस्तान की मदद करता क्योंकि न्यूक्लियर
blackmailing was taking place.  So the first
ब्लैकमेलिंग हो रही थी। तो सबसे पहला जो
objective was that Pakistan would
ऑब्जेक्टिव था ना क्योंकि पाकिस्तान कुछ
not have been able to do anything if we had attacked it.
भी नहीं कर सकता था अगर हम उसके ऊपर हमला
Secondly then you would
करते हम उसके ऊपर अटैक करते। दूसरा फिर आप
say that the whole world would jump on this.
कहते कि पूरी दुनिया सर इस पे कूद पड़ती।
America would have jumped, Europe would have jumped.
अमेरिका कूद पड़ता, यूरोप कूद पड़ता।
See who was carrying out this attack?  Israel was getting it done.
देखिए यह हमला कौन करवा रहा था? इजराइल
And we all know that
करवा रहा था। और हम सबको पता है कि
America and Israel support each other.
अमेरिका और इजराइल एक दूसरे के सपोर्ट में
America always
हैं। हमेशा अमेरिका जो है वो इजराइल के
supports Israel.  So if Israel had done it, it is
सपोर्ट में रहता है। तो अगर इजराइल करवाता
obvious that America would have supported it.
तो जाहिर सी बात है अमेरिका सपोर्ट में
Now, as far as the whole world is concerned, even
रहता। अब जहां तक पूरी दुनिया की बात है
if we were to assume that it could
अगर मान लीजिए हम ये मान भी लेते कि चलो
put pressure on India, it has been
भारत के ऊपर प्रेशर बनाती तो वो तो हमेशा
doing so since always.  After 1998, America
से ही बना रही है। 1998 के बाद अमेरिका ने
imposed many sanctions on India.
ढेरों सेंशंस लगा दिए थे भारत के ऊपर।
But later we realised that we
लेकिन बाद में पता चला कि भारत के बिना हम
cannot survive without India.  So that has been
चल ही नहीं सकते। तो वो तो हमेशा से ही
happening forever.  Today you can see
होता जा रहा है। आज ईरान में आप देख सकते
what is happening in Iran.  Brother, look, literally
हैं क्या हो रहा है। भाई देखो लिटरली
America and Israel are doing hooliganism.
अमेरिका इजराइल गुंडागर्दी कर रहे हैं।
Literally brother, they are saying surrender,
लिटरली भाई वो कह रहे हैं सरेंडर करो
surrender, we will finish you off, we will kill you.  Iran is
सरेंडर करो खत्म कर देंगे मार देंगे। ईरान
fine whatever its regime is.  But
ठीक है वो उसकी रिजीम जैसी भी है। लेकिन
now someone is saying something.  Donald
अब ये तो तो कोई कुछ बोल रहा है। डॉनल्ड
Trump comes publicly abusing Emmanuel Macron.
ट्रंप सरेआम इमैनुअल मैक्रो को गरिया के आ
Russia is openly killing Ukraine.  If there are
जाते हैं। रशिया खुलेआम यूक्रेन को मार
sensations then there are sensations.  No one is
रहा है। सेंशंस लगे तो लगे हैं। कोई कुछ
saying anything.  You look at China.   The
नहीं कह रहा है। चाइना को आप देखिए।
world does not say this, brother, everyone is concerned about their own interests.  At that
दुनिया नहीं कहती भाई सबको अपने इंटरेस्ट
time we felt that
की पड़ी होती है। उस समय हमको यह लगा कि
brother, we have the problem of Punjab.   There
भैया हमारे पास पंजाब की प्रॉब्लम है।
is a problem of Kashmir.  Ok?  And then
कश्मीर की प्रॉब्लम है। ठीक है? और फिर
what will the world say after that?  There will be a problem.  There
उसके बाद दुनिया क्या कहेगी? प्रॉब्लम हो
is pressure.  we stopped.  But
जाएगी। प्रेशर है। हम रुक गए। लेकिन
when you actually look at it, it doesn't have any meaning.
एक्चुअल में जब आप देखो तो इसका कोई मायने
Brother, the Kashmir problem: if
है ही नहीं। भाई कश्मीर की प्रॉब्लम अगर
we had destroyed Pakistan's nuclear program, then
हम पाकिस्तान का न्यूक्लियर प्रोग्राम
Kashmir and Pakistan would have been even more scared.
तबाह करते तो कश्मीर पाकिस्तान और डर
That problem would also have ended.  Because
जाता। वो प्रॉब्लम भी खत्म होती। क्योंकि
then India could fight war as many times as it wanted.
फिर भारत जितनी बार चाहे उतनी बार वॉर कर
Today, which country in the entire Middle East or
सकता था। आज इजराइल पूरे मिडिल ईस्ट को
West Asia is
वेस्ट एशिया को कौन सा देश है जो इजराइल
not afraid of Israel?  Hit Syria.  There was a
से नहीं डरता है? सीरिया को मारा। सीरिया
coup in Syria.  Today, the terrorist on whom America had a
में तख्ता पलट करवा दिया। अमेरिका का आज
bounty of millions of dollars was
डॉलर्स में इनाम था उसी को ही प्रेसिडेंट
made the President of Syria.  Donald Trump just
बना दिया सीरिया में। डॉनल्ड ट्रंप अभी
met him.  You look at Iraq,
उससे मिले थे। आप इराक को देख लीजिए
America destroyed it.  Jordan
अमेरिका ने तबाह कर दिया। जॉर्डन अमेरिका
stands with America.  Lebanon was devastated.
के साथ खड़ा हुआ है। लेबनॉन को तबाह कर
Israel will take over the whole of Gaza.
दिया। गाज़ा इजराइल पूरा का पूरा ले लेगा।
Egypt is silent out of fear.  He is not
इजिप्ट डर के मारे चुप है। कुछ भी नहीं
saying anything.  Is it okay?  Here in Kuwait, the
बोल रहा है। ठीक है ना? इधर कुवैत ये गल्फ
entire Gulf is
पूरा का पूरा गल्फ जो है वो अमेरिका की
under the grip of America.  is supporting America.
चपेट में है। अमेरिका का साथ दे रही है।
Iran is already seeing devastation in the entire Gulf country.
पूरे गल्फ कंट्री ईरान को ऑलरेडी तबाही
So who is left?  You
देख ही रहा है ईरान। तो बचा ही कौन? आप
can see that the situation in Afghanistan is also
देख सकते हैं अफगानिस्तान में भी हालात
very bad and very soon America will
बहुत खराब है और बहुत जल्द जो है अमेरिका
support Afghanistan also.  So you
अफगानिस्तान का भी साथ दे देगा। तो आप
see, everyone in Israel is scared.
देखिए इजराइल जो है ये सब के सब डरे हुए
Nobody messes with Israel.  Why?
हैं। कोई इजराइल से नहीं उलझता है। क्यों?
Because these people do not have nuclear power.
क्योंकि इन लोगों के पास न्यूक्लियर पावर
And the day Iran
नहीं है। और जिस दिन ईरान के पास
gets nuclear power, the power balance will
न्यूक्लियर पावर आ जाएगी पावर बैलेंस
completely shift.  On that day, Iran
बिल्कुल शिफ्ट हो जाएगा। उस दिन ईरान जो
can do anything and will say, now
है वो कुछ भी कर सकता है और बोलेगा अब
kill us.  Now you have the guts, try killing them, then Israel will
मारो। अब औकात है मार के देखो तब इजराइल
not attack.  This was the strategy India
हमला नहीं करेगा। यही भारत स्ट्रेटजी अपना
could have adopted.  However, we are not as aggressive as Israel.
सकता था। हम हालांकि इजराइल जैसे अग्रेसर
Nor are we a revisionist nation.
नहीं है। ना ही हम रिवीजनिस्ट देश हैं।
But we will have to work on our defense.  Ever
लेकिन हमको अपने डिफेंस में तो काम करना
since
ही पड़ेगा। लगातार 1947 से जब से
Pakistan was formed in 1947, it has continuously created problems in Kashmir.
पाकिस्तान बना है, कश्मीर में प्रॉब्लम
He has created problems in India.  We
उसने क्रिएट की है। हम बहुत ही स्ट्रांग
could have taken very strong action and the entire
एक्शन ले सकते थे और ना ही कोई पूरी
world would not have said anything and Pakistan would have
दुनिया कहती और पाकिस्तान भी अपनी औकात
remained within its limits.  Suppose if Pakistan was
में रहता। मान लीजिए पाकिस्तान न्यूक्लियर
not a nuclear power then Pahalgam would have been attacked on 22nd April.  We would have
पावर नहीं होता तो और 22 अप्रैल को पहलगाव
destroyed the entire Pakistan.  The
हमला हो गया होता। पूरा पाकिस्तान तोड़ के
whole of Pakistan, but India
रख देते। पूरा पाकिस्तान लेकिन भारत ने
increased the restraint.  And friends,
रिस्ट्रेंट बढ़ता। और यही दोस्तों 2001
in 2001, Pakistan attacked our Parliament with the same thing, Operation Parakram.
में सेम चीज ऑपरेशन पराक्रम हमारे
Nuclear Power: As soon as
पाकिस्तान ने। न्यूक्लियर पावर जैसे ही
Pakistan became a nuclear power, its attacks
पाकिस्तान न्यूक्लियर पावर बना उसके हमले
increased 10 times.  He
10 गुना ज्यादा तेज हो गए। उसने भारत में
started sending terrorists to India.  Now
आतंकवादियों को भेजना शुरू कर दिया। अब
what happened in that?  What happened was that
उसमें हुआ क्या? उसमें ये हुआ कि ऑपरेशन
under Operation Parakram, the Indian Army was ready to
पराक्रम के तहत इंडियन आर्मी वाज़ रेडी टू
attack Pakistan.
अटैक पाकिस्तान।
But Atal Bihari Vajpayee and the senior
लेकिन अटल बिहारी वाजपेयी या सीनियर
leadership all said that
लीडरशिप सब ने ये बोल दिया कि स्ट्रेटेजिक
you have to maintain strategic restraint.  You step back.  There was
रिस्ट्रेंट आपको बरतनी है। आप पीछे हट
no response from above.
जाइए। ऊपर से जवाब नहीं आया।
And same with Manmohan Singh.  So this is what has been happening to
और यही मनमोहन सिंह के साथ। तो लगातार यही
us continuously.  Somewhere
हुआ है हमारे साथ। हम कहीं ना कहीं उस चीज
we know from that thing that nuclear war is
से हमको पता है कि न्यूक्लियर वॉर सही
not right.  So I think my analysis
नहीं है। तो मेरे ख्याल में मेरा एनालिसिस
says that as many articles are being published right now,
यही कहता है कि जो अभी काफी आर्टिकल छप
India and Israel should have jointly
रहे हैं कि तो इंडिया और इज़राइल को मिलकर
attacked Pakistan's nuclear program even today if they still have the opportunity.
हमला करना चाहिए था और अगर अभी भी मौका
Ok?  And even now if you get this
मिले। ठीक है? और अभी भी अगर आपके पास ये
opportunity then in my opinion you should attack.  You should
मौका आए तो मेरे ख्याल में हमला कर देना
not think about it because if you
चाहिए। सोचना नहीं चाहिए क्योंकि अगर आप
give even a small window to Pakistan, it will
पाकिस्तान को जरा सा भी विंडो देंगे वो
spread terrorism in the whole world and will not do anything else.
आतंकवादी फैलाएगा और कुछ भी नहीं करने
Look at Hamas, now
वाला वो पूरी दुनिया में। हमास देखिए अब
Iran funds Hamas.  Hamas
ईरान हमास को फंड करता है। हमास पाकिस्तान
went to Pakistan.  What did Pakistan do?  Pahalgaon was
गया। पाकिस्तान ने क्या किया? पहलगांव
attacked.  Exactly in our style.
हमला कराया। एकदम हमा स्टाइल में। दुनिया
Terrorists across the world
भर के आतंकवादी जो हैं वो पाकिस्तान से
seek help from Pakistan.  You will definitely find Pakistan's link with
मदद मांगते हैं। आपको पाकिस्तान का लिंक
terrorism.  What do you
मिलेगा ही मिलेगा आतंकवाद से। आपको क्या
think?  Please let me know in the comment box.
लगता है? मुझे कमेंट बॉक्स में जरूर
Be happy, keep reading.  Desh
बताइएगा। खुश रहिए, पढ़ते रहिए। देश
Siddhant Agnitri signing off.
सिद्धांत अग्नित्री साइनिंग ऑफ।